Winds are blowing
real hard right now.
They have been all
day. It's a change.
Some winds of change.
Look at that ant pile.
Yeah.
So I just woke up to
probably 100, 150 baboons.
You see a bunch over there.
Bunch of them here in trees,
you can see them moving around.
In the back of my
head, I'm just thinking,
"Uh-oh, what's coming?"
I got a bad feeling.
Really bad feeling.
Seven days into
the 35-day challenge.
Yes! I got it!
Frank's arrow hit its mark...
It's dinner time!
Yeah, buddy!
...providing his team
with the first big protein
win of the challenge.
Yum.
But also attracting
the attention
of hungry predators.
Hey!
Last night, something
or several somethings
definitely were scoping
us out for dinner.
So we need to get more prepared.
We got to build
up our boma more.
Even though our thunder
bom is pretty solid,
it can always be more solid.
I’ll grab this Vespa.
We need to make sure
that we are absolutely secure
and we have all the metal
surrounding us because lions
are very pro-safety.
If they think they're gonna
get hurt, they're not gonna
jump over the boma.
Home repairs.
You know, keeping
up with the Joneses.
We got to add
whatever metal we can.
Anything to give us a
buffer zone from the things
that want to eat us out here.
Good luck to any lions
that try to come over there.
We've actually added
about two and a half
to three feet of height
to our boma, and probably
another 2, 300 pounds.
Not to mention...
it looks pretty sick right now.
We got some cloud cover today.
Thank you, Jesus.
The past, what? Three days?
It was well over 100 degrees.
Honestly, I'm really worried
about that meat spoiling.
This weather here,
I wouldn't think it's
the best for biltong.
You just need hot, dry days.
That concerns me a
little bit, so we may have
to resort to smoking it.
We're going to have to move
a fire inside this and then use
the heat and the smoke
to just continue drying it out.
We'll turn this Jeep
Model T into a smoker.
We got strands of copper wire
that was inside
of some vehicles.
I could use the copper
wire to sew them together.
-Wrap them around?
-Yeah.
I like it.
So now I have to make cordage.
To help me do this, I'm just
gonna kinda crack this stuff up,
seeing as how I got all
these fine tools at my disposal.
An eight-pound wedge and
a 10-pound hammerhead.
It's this casing on this wire,
is a little bit
dried out and old.
Yeah, it just peels right off.
I'll start pulling
this meat down.
-Yeah.
Just strip that wire,
because it is strand copper.
And we can get
all that in there,
probably just off
this one piece of wire.
-Yeah, yeah.
-You know?
So I'm literally just
wrapping this around
and then giving it a twist,
and it'll just make
basically just a quad of meat
hanging off a little tiny wire.
So it'll just slowly have
smoke trickling through it
to keep the flies out,
And shelter from the
rain and the elements,
so we can fire this thing up
and get a coal
smoke going on here.
-Yeah!
-Woohoo! Smoker!
This biltong is gonna
help get us through
to the next kill.
And God willing, it
happens within a few days,
because that
stuff will go quick.
Never seen one of those
on "Naked and Afraid."
I've never seen one
of them anywhere.
Yeah, yeah.
Our meat is safe.
I hope.
Aye, aye, aye.
It still hurts a
good bit, but...
I don't know.
Trying not to feel
completely useless.
The irritation still
continues, but my eye is
no longer throbbing as
distractingly, and that means
that I'll be able to
get up and do stuff.
I'm at the point in
my lack of calories
where standing
up makes me dizzy.
So try and move slow,
especially standing up slow.
After discovering signs
of a deadly predator...
Look at the lion print.
Bro, look at the size of that!
Our boma is right there.
I want all of this barbed wire.
...Waz and Teal worked
to secure their new shelter.
While I was doing
some of this wiring,
one of the pieces came
back and kinda hit my eye.
Yep.
But an injury to Teal's eye...
threatened to end her challenge.
I'm going back up
to the farmhouse.
So, Teal, even though she's
not physically feeling good,
she always wants to feel
like she's doing something.
And I'm not really surprised,
to be honest with you.
That's just who she
is as a survivalist.
We got a lot of work to do.
Yeah.
We sure could use some food.
It's step by step.
It's keep pushing forward,
which is absolutely integral
in this doomsday scenario.
All right, let's do
plans for the day.
What do you got on?
Food is still our
main goal, obviously.
But I'd like to go
get the kitchen sink.
I think it's time for it
to move down here.
-OK.
-I want to bring down a barrel
to hang the meat off of
-to smoke it.
-Yes.
I need an extra set of
hands for the sink, at least.
-Yeah, I can do that.
-If you're up for it.
The way I see it, once the
kill happens, it's go time.
And the best way is
to be prepared for it.
We'll have everything ready.
The processing will go quickly.
Hopefully, that will get all
the meat ready in enough time
for it not to spoil.
I'm really hoping
this burns off.
Because, if we get a hot day,
then that water hole
is going to be real busy.
So, that's what I'm
hoping happens.
We've got hunting
on the agenda today,
that's been on the agenda
for the last few days.
I'm going to go down
to the water hole,
and then we can set up a blind
and hunt down at the water hole,
and hopefully get some
red meat in our bellies.
And once we finally
harvest an animal,
we need a real nice streamlined
process where we save
as much meat as possible.
And there's things up at
the house that we can use
down here at the boma
to process that animal.
Yeah, I think that one's
still got a top and bottom.
Well, we need a top, don't we?
I'd rather not have a
top, so we can hang stuff
-from around the edge and stuff?
-Yeah, yeah.
I want to bring down the
sink from the farmhouse.
And I want to set it up so
that we can wash a few things
in the sink down here.
All that now and
the kitchen sink.
-You look like Atlas...
-Heh.
...carrying the world
on your shoulders.
We know it's gonna
take many trips,
but we hope it's worth it.
Sweet.
The only thing we're
missing is the meat.
I'll fix that.
Isn't that fancy?
I'm going to head
down to the water hole.
The other day, we could
see a real big male kudu.
And so the fact that
there's animals down there,
the fact that there's
water down there,
I'm gonna set up a blind.
I've really just used stuff
that's close to that area.
When I was using
the other blind,
I'd pop up from behind
the blind and they'd see me,
whereas right here...
I can ever so silently
come across into my window
Woosh!
Straight down there.
I want to be out of the
sun as much as possible,
just gather up some stuff
from around, basically,
just enlarging the structure
that was already there
so I can move
around a little bit,
and the animals can't see me.
And the thought process there
is also I don't want to change
that environment too much.
I don't want to be
bringing in all this new stuff
that's gonna stop the
animals from coming in,
so I just built up
the same shape
a little bit bigger and
hopefully that helps.
I'm just gonna post up here
and see what else comes in,
hopefully something
comes in this little window
and we get some dinner.
I'm going to just cut this here.
With this piece of hose, I
can create a drainage system,
and then that way it'll divert
all the blood and all the guts
and all the organs
that are from the sink
away from the boma,
but this whole sink
full of water keeps the meat
from being covered in flies,
and allows us to make
sure it's properly washed
before we cut it up
and put it in the smoker.
Pour some water in the
sink and see if it works.
I'm delighted, it works.
I got a bad feeling.
We got some nasty
stuff coming in.
I'm so glad you
got the wriggly tin.
Yeah.
Reminds you of home.
Uh-huh.
Competing with a crocodile
for limited resources,
Wes and Stee built a modern
take on a primitive fish trap.
That looks fantastic.
Something doesn't feel right.
But malnourishment
led to the exits of both
Miranda and Kel.
It just highlights how
hard it is to survive here.
Yeah.
We are hungry, and we
need some sort of fish
or red meat ASAP.
Stee's W trap was built
with sheets of roofing tin
to guide fish into a
closed section of the pond
where they can't escape
and the crocodile
can't reach them.
I can't believe active
fishing is not working,
'cause you can sit here quietly
and watch the fish in there.
Maybe we'll make a couple
smaller ones.
You know, in the days
that we've been here,
we're scavenging so much stuff.
It gives such an opportunity
for us to advance our survival.
Yep. That's the
thin stuff, right?
Yep.
I think you're gonna like that.
I feel much more
hopeful about that.
All right, let's go fish.
Yeah, I'll pretty much
settle for anything, buddy.
Yeah.
We probably tried
seven different things
to catch fish.
I'm frustrated, but we
gotta get some food.
It's just gonna take
a little extra effort.
All right, nice.
I don't know if
it's good or not.
It's a little fly bug.
I'm going to give him a try.
And we wait.
It's never been
this windy before.
I hope it means rain,
but this thing's holding strong.
It is sturdy, and it's pretty.
A little rugged, just like me.
This is the hard part of
the solo challenge, man.
I'm tired.
Surviving alone
since day four...
I'm going to deconstruct
this boma here,
and then I'm gonna just
reassemble them for a blind.
...Joe turned his old
camp into a hunting blind.
What is that sound?
But the arrival of a
young bull elephant...
...has him on his heels.
Hunger is a big motivator
right now, and I just need
to rain or shine,
get in that blind,
and get some kills
so that I can continue to
have the nourishment I need
to keep my strength
and my mind going.
The elephants came in,
knocked the tree down,
tore it down, right where I sit,
right in the blind.
Every single time
I try to come up
some way to survive out here,
it just keeps ending
up back to square one.
Africa does not
care for your plans.
That is a fact.
If you were to ask
me before I came here,
my top predators
to be afraid of,
elephant wouldn't
even have made the list.
But now that he's
just the silent stalker
in the night, and the
thrasher of my blind,
I feel like he's got a
personal vendetta out for me.
Now I gotta spend more
calories fixing, fixing things.
But I have a feeling
that this ain't gonna be it.
It's just a reminder
that out here,
anything can happen.
This entire apocalyptic
challenge does not give a crap
about your agenda
or your plans, man.
So you just gotta
keep on pushing
and making problem solving
and making things work out here.
Having to rebuild the blind
after the elephants trashed it,
like, you know, my energy
level is just depleting so fast.
No.
Boy, this fishing has sucked.
We've tried every bait,
different size hooks,
and they're just not
interested, and I think
I'm just gonna change
these static passive lines.
This landscape is too deadly.
It's an apocalypse.
There's barely any food.
The sun is relentless.
I'm going to go eat half
a dozen mopane leaves.
I bet you I haven't had
300 calories since I got here.
Desperate times call
for desperate measures.
Oh, my favorite.
So the ends of the mopane,
new branches are edible,
but it tastes like
absolute crap.
This tree is actually
quite awesome because...
if it feels like it's
being under attack,
like I'm doing right now,
it surges tannins.
And the tannins go in the leaves
and make it, like,
virtually inedible.
So you gotta take off
a bunch, and then stop,
and that's what you eat.
What's even cooler is if
there are other mopane trees
in the area,
somehow, it tells them
it's under attack, and
they push out tannins, too.
It's amazing.
Although high in protein,
it would take over five cups
of mopane leaves to provide
the same amount of calories
as one carrot.
Back in the day, tribes
during tough times
would survive on these.
So I figured if they can, I can.
All right.
That's good for now.
I don't want too
much acid in my gut.
Will have bad effects.
Mm, ooh!
Yeah, it's not pleasant, though.
The clouds, looks like
it might get really bad.
Well, that doesn't sound good.
She might turn.
Obviously, there has been
no rain for a very long time
in this area.
So we just need to figure
out a roof over our head.
If there is a storm, we
have vehicles to get into.
If we're going to use
these two for shelter,
they've both got
roofs, so we're cool.
We just need to figure
out where we're gonna put
the firewood to keep it dry,
where we're gonna put the fire,
and how to preserve the embers.
Mm-hmm.
And I mean, that's easy enough.
-I mean...
-We can take coals
out of there when
the rain starts,
-put them in there.
-Yeah, OK.
Yeah.
I think we're, I mean,
more prepared than most,
I would say.
Yeah, we're
definitely getting there.
-Hey, how are you?
-Yeah, not bad,
for sitting for an
hour and a half
and not seeing an animal.
-Not a one, huh?
-Not a one.
The weather has a
massive effect on hunting.
Animals don't move
around as much.
When there's a lot of
cloud, and when there's a lot
of pockets of wind coming in,
they sort of just hunker down
and stay in their area.
I wonder if it'll rain today.
Maybe it'll clear up.
I'm guessing probably not,
but one can always hope.
Well, I got my first rain.
I think overall, I'll be fine,
if it stays a light rain, so...
I'll just curl up by the fire.
Staying... staying nice
and dry, so that part's good.
We've woken up to a light
sprinkling on the shelter,
and it is pretty cold outside,
and it is pretty warm in here,
so that's a good...
box check for us.
Grateful for the fire and
all the wood we have.
Our nice boma.
The temperature has
massively dropped.
A little chilly,
actually, but it's, like,
nice and warm in here.
But not overly toasty,
so we can feel the
temperatures dipping outside.
Can't even feel it in here.
I'm so jealous of Steven
because he can sleep
through bloody anything.
Everything is wet.
It's gonna be a long night.
We made it through
a miserable night.
Ugh!
Stop drizzling!
It was literally
110 plus degrees
the past three days, and now...
...you can see my breath.
I mean, the cars will work
to get us out of the heavy rain,
but you know, I
would like some kind
of a awning or overhang.
You know, just with a bunch
of debris on it, you know,
'cause I think a
debris roof would work
for like this.
It'd be a manufactured
shade, too, so...
Dual purpose. I like it.
Yeah, dual purpose, yeah.
I think we need to, like,
get this canopy sorted,
because it doesn't make
for a good night's sleep at all.
It's just sprinkles.
I know it's cold, I
know it's drizzly,
but I still slept like a baby.
This rain's annoying,
but it's nothing to
write home about.
Well, it looks like we finally
got a little break in the rain,
and it warmed up a little bit.
I'm going to head to
that other watering hole.
I'm going to try
to hunt half day.
I know, like, the
weather conditions
aren't the best for
hunting right now, but...
We also need food, so, you know.
When you get a big
kill, it doesn't last long.
When you end up
getting to just the biltong,
just the dried meat,
you need to always
keep bringing food in.
You don't depend on the reserve.
The reserve is emergency food.
So, while Lex and Frank get
some things done on our canopy,
feel like it's a good
day to take the bow
and give a crack at it.
First I need your help
getting that gutter down.
OK, sounds good.
Looking at our shelter,
yeah, I think it's waterproof,
but if it was a heavy rain,
all that water could
come in under our shelter.
It's because we can use
the man-made resources
rather than just
the primal stuff.
I did notice there's some
gutter up at the old house.
I'm going to go back up
there, see if I can't scavenge
a few pieces that I can add
onto the back of our shelter
and catch that water.
OK, I'm climbing up
on your shoulders.
Not only do I have to get
on his shoulders and climb up
the wall of the farmhouse,
but I have to figure out a way
to detach the
gutter from the roof
while I'm up there.
I'm not a circus performer,
I'm not a cheerleader,
and I don't know
if I wanna do this.
Slowly.
Walking slowly, slowly, slowly.
OK, all the way up.
-Lean forwards?
-Yep.
-OK, that's all the way up.
-OK.
-You uncomfortable?
-No, I'm cruising.
OK.
This is not a good idea.
I'm envisioning myself
falling and landing
in these huge
bushes full of thorns.
Don't look up
-because there's tons of rust.
-OK, hold it, hold it.
It's 100% bolted down
there... I can see it.
I'll just bring you down.
Oh, they're bolted
to each other.
That's what I just... yeah.
It worked so perfectly
up until that point.
I'm getting to the point
now where I don't even know
if this is going to work.
Am I wasting all this energy?
Am I getting rid of
all these calories?
I just need to cut from like
here down to the bottom.
But we need to make
adjustments to the shelter
to make sure it's waterproof.
Yes!
-There we go.
-Yay.
-Ooh, that was a battle.
I must admit, I did not have
on my challenge bingo card
looking like a pirate zombie
and standing on a
giant's shoulders.
All right. Let's do it.
Been overcast all
day, a little misty.
I got to check
that passive line.
And now that's getting wet,
don't wanna slip on these rocks.
That would be game over.
I'm hoping this changing
weather will change my luck.
Right now, anything
would be good.
I'd be willing to bet that
croc took it and took my hook
and wrapped it around something.
Fishing is terrible.
Nothing is biting.
If something's not working,
you gotta change
strategies, you know?
It's good to have a plan,
but you gotta be very willing
to change your
plan if it isn't working,
especially in this
kind of landscape.
Right now, I'm collecting
some dung beetles
from this fresh dung.
And I'm probably gonna
cook them and eat them.
You know you're hungry
when you're picking
through some animal's
crap to find something to eat.
That's a big one.
Desperate times call
for desperate measures.
I'm here to survive,
and survival isn't
pretty sometimes.
Sometimes you even have to eat.
Dung beetles feed off
the solid waste of animals
and provide almost the
same amount of protein
per ounce as chicken eggs.
But it must be cooked
thoroughly to destroy
harmful bacteria and parasites.
None of them are moving, right?
All right.
Cheers, mate.
Tastes a bit salty.
Edible.
I keep having an
after flavor of sour milk.
Yeah, that's not good.
All right, that's cool.
We need some
sort of food source.
I find nothing
objectionable about this.
I think they're delicious. Mmm.
I feel quite good.
I think we can use
this just to get rid
of most of the problem now.
Just thinking about different
ways I can get it in here
nice and easy.
There's tons of wire
still in the old corral.
-Yeah.
-That's the wire I need.
A little bit farther
from our boma,
there's a cattle corral.
And that has wire, barbed wire,
so many things that we
can use to put the gutter on.
Haven’t been in this area.
A little scary, to be honest.
The farther I get from the
boma, the more I get, like,
worried that something
else is watching me.
I'm, like, totally getting
in my own head right now.
Woo!
Deep breaths here.
Nothing is going
to eat you today.
Oh, God.
Is that a lion?
What is that?
Is that a rock? Oh my
God, I'm losing my mind.
Am I hallucinating?
Oh my God, I think that's a...
I think that's a kudu.
Do kudus sleep during the day?
I mean, surely
it's not alive, right?
Please don't wake him up.
Oh my god, if he wakes
up and starts charging me,
I'm gonna lose my mind.
It's dead, Teal,
it's dead, it's dead.
Just touch it.
It's dead.
Oh...
I think that's a kudu.
I mean, surely
it's not alive, right?
Oh, my god, if he wakes
up and starts charging me,
I'm gonna lose my mind.
It's dead, Teal.
It's dead, it's dead.
Just touch it.
Oh...
Oh, my gosh, it's still wiggly.
Oh, my God, we
could probably eat this.
I gotta tell Waz.
Gotta tell Waz.
Waz!
-Waz!
-What's up?
I found food!
OK, slow down, slow down.
I thought you were getting
chased by a lion right now.
I was waiting to come
out and fight a lion.
-What'd you find?
-I found a dead kudu.
Ooh, you think this one's good?
Yeah, why don't you come see?
All right, let's go look at it.
-You got a knife?
-Yeah, I do.
I picked it up when I
thought I was gonna
fight a lion right now.
OK.
I thought maybe it
was something that,
like, you wounded, but I
don't see any holes or nothing.
Not a nick to her.
What happens if he's
died of something?
Well, it doesn't matter.
We cook the food anyway.
So even if it's died of
something like a disease
or something like
that, we cook it.
It's fine.
Shall we just try
to pull it together?
Is that stupid?
I'm not even going to be
able to lift this up a tree.
So...
So then we just
straddle them open.
Shew!
It's absolutely impossible to
get this thing back to camp.
This thing weighs 200 pounds.
There's no way that we could
do anything but field-dress it
right here where it lays.
The other thing I'm worried
about is the smell of this
-going out, you know?
-Yeah.
This dead kudu certainly is
going to attract other animals,
perhaps hyenas or other
scavengers, maybe even lions,
because it's still very fresh.
So to a lion, it might just
smell like a distressed animal
instead of it being a carcass.
So we need to be sure
that we're looking
around ourselves
as often as possible.
And if there's any
sign of danger,
we need to get out of here.
This is the stomach
right here, and... oh!
I tell you what,
this is warm inside.
Yeah?
This might be
fresher than I thought.
You might have found this...
only just after it
died, you know?
Why has it died?
There's a couple of different
things that I can possibly
think of, a snake bite,
or something like that.
But more probable is the
fact that all of these trees have
new little buds, green
buds growing on them.
Those green buds
are full of tannins.
Ingesting too many tannins
at once can create ulcers
in the mouth and
intestines of animals,
and in very high doses,
can lead to kidney
failure and even death.
-Mwah.
-Just drop it.
All right, so that's
the heart right there.
All these little pieces are
gonna be very hard to carry.
Yeah, let's get this skin.
This big stretch of pelt will
allow us to put all the little
organs we want in and
carry it back without having
to take many trips.
Here we go.
I'm cold and...
I can't do it anymore because
I'm gonna pass out here soon.
The biggest thing we're
fighting is our energy levels
because we haven't
eaten in 13 days.
So even though we have
all this food right in front of us,
it's not helping us do the
work that we have to do to get
the food inside of us.
We can each take a quarter,
skin it, prepare the meat.
I will say at least
it doesn't stink.
It just smells like steak.
And we need to be careful.
Keep our head on a swivel.
You know, I build my blind,
the elephant smashes it.
I rebuild it, and now
the watering hole is
just not a place where
animals are gathering.
Between the elements
and elephants, it feels like
I'm taking one step forward
and two steps back every day.
I don't really believe in curses
but there's some other force
at work here that's
just trying to keep me
from succeeding.
It's time to be born
again, hardcore.
I have to really dig deep,
and I've got to do everything
that I can so that I can
stay in this challenge.
I'm gonna get through
this stronger than ever.
There's a catfish as big
as my arm in this thing.
At least my forearm.
Oh, yeah, still good.
Oh! Look at that.
Look at that!
Still alive.
Good, good.
Oh-ho-ho-ho!
This is...
What a blessing.
This is incredible.
Absolutely incredible.
Trying...
to just gather my thoughts.
Here you go. In
the pot, my friend.
This is what it
means to be out here.
I've got a full meal.
Something I wasn't expecting.
That... that trap
gave us nothing for...
for days, and now...
now it's just giving me...
more food than I've
ever had on a challenge.
So I'm grateful
of this first meal.
Oh, that meat looks
so fresh and tender.
Oh, my goodness.
So good.
This miracle of this fish
getting into this basket,
like, it is, you know...
It's uh...
It's, uh...
This is gonna give me
such needed nourishment.
This is gonna give
me the strength I need
to keep going.
Steven is out there giving
hunting a crack today.
He is an absolute veteran
when it comes to Africa.
You're almost there.
Huh, huh, huh.
Hey!
Good job, Lex.
In his experience,
these storms usually
come in quick and fast.
And so he doesn't seem
to be too concerned about it.
But I am not going
home from the cold.
Timber!
So Frank and I are
gonna build the canopy.
Combining natural resources
and scavenged
man-made materials,
the canopy will use
five chopped trees
as support poles,
anchored to the car
frames with metal wire.
Smaller branches will
be placed across the top
in a lattice pattern,
which will support
and other debris
to fill in the canopy.
It's a lot of work to
chop down nine trees
and then drag them
back to the boma.
Good job, Lex.
Ooh! I've given myself
a nice little blood blister
-under there.
-Blood blister.
I will finish what I started.
Damn, girl.
Every day is about trying
to improve our situation
just that tiny bit more.
A lot of calories in this.
I hope that Steven
can get some food.
-Oh, my God!
-I was right there.
Ugh... Damn it.
Not disappointed,
this is hunting.
This is, like, whether
you're hunting in Africa
or in the States,
you have to...
you have to deal
with these situations.
That's just how it is.
Have to be positive because
that's what you have to be
in any survival situation,
let alone this one.
And this is the toughest
ones, I've experienced yet.
Ooh! My triceps is sore.
-Hacking?
-Yeah.
I feel like I've had a workout.
-What up?
-How goes it?
Well, I saw warthogs,
and that was it.
-That was about it.
-That's not good.
This looks awesome! Holy shoot!
This looks amazing!
Yep.
We got the structure up.
It's not entirely finished yet.
Tomorrow, we're gonna
look for just really bushy limbs
with a bunch of leaves on them.
We'll just pile them up
there indiscriminately,
and we got protection
from this wet, nasty weather.
Dude, it looks
absolutely phenomenal.
Absolutely phenomenal.
Ohh!
That was a haul.
That's a lot of work.
That's a heavy animal,
but, at the same time,
I'm feeling blessed.
It's a rarity when you're
practicing survival like this
-to get given a gift.
-Yeah.
And we've got lots of meat
inside that meat sack there.
By cooking some, over the
fire and eating it, it's gonna bump
our endorphins and energy
levels up, and that's gonna
allow us to do the rest of
it clearheaded and faster.
OK.
We're gonna start off with just
grilling some straight up,
because we need to
get some in our body
as quickly as possible.
So we're gonna grill
some backstrap really fast.
If we can get some in
real quick, it might help us
this afternoon, this
evening, as we're still trying
to process the rest.
-Ooh!
-Want some?
Yeah.
This is my first
piece of kudu ever.
It looks phenomenal.
Oh, look at that.
Look at that red
meat endorphin rush.
Mm...
-Cooked to perfection.
-That's super tender.
It just does
something to your soul.
I can feel it in my body.
I can feel the
strength coming back.
I can feel my...
abilities coming back.
So we can't just cut strips
and draw it on a bush.
The flies will get it.
So we are gonna have to smoke
everything we have left.
In an apocalyptic environment,
I feel like we have to use
a lot of the
resources around us,
absolutely everything
available to us.
So we're gonna have
to build a smoker.
We have a 50 gallon barrel
with some fire
in the bottom of it.
I've got a hole in
the bottom of that
where I can feed a log in.
On top of that barrel,
we've got a grate.
Then I put another
50 gallon barrel on top.
That one on top, we've got
lots of wire that goes down,
across and back up
and it hooks on the top.
And all the way along, and
at the bottom of that wire,
we have meat hanging in there.
So it's exposed to the
heat, it's not too close
to the coals, and there's a
lot of smoke coming up over it.
We're on the clock
with all this stuff,
with the sun out how it is.
So, back to work.
We have to make meat hangers,
and they have to
hang on the barrel.
I mean, I'd love for this
meat to last 20 more days,
but unless we make
a lot of effort now
in preserving it, it won't.
With every new accomplishment,
comes a new challenge.
It's funny how that works.
Nothing's easy in Africa.
So right now, Waz is
finishing up prepping
one of the hind
legs of the kudu.
We're going to try
to smoke it whole.
The way we've got
the barrels set up,
we should be able to hang it.
And as long as we can preserve
the outer portion of the meat,
it will protect
the inner portion.
We have to keep the
temperature perfect.
We have to make sure
there's enough smoke and nail it
in one go, which if we don't
do, we might lose this, maybe.
We just got a real light flame,
that'll go out there in a
second and it's just gonna be...
it's just gonna be
charcoal and smoke.
And I'll just have to
keep coming out all night
and making sure
that that all gets...
that all stays where it is,
doesn't get too hot,
doesn't get too cold,
doesn't lose the smoke.
Hunting out here has been tough.
It really has.
I've seen quite a bit of game,
but nothing inside of, like,
Thirty, 35 yards.
And so it makes
it really difficult.
That's a long way
to shoot a long bow.
And the lazy W trap,
it's not working at all.
A couple of guinea fowl came in,
but not close enough.
All right.
Stee has these big ideas,
and a lot of them are great,
and a lot of them
put us in harm's way.
Yeah.
We've got our lazy W trap.
We get that metal sheet,
and then we both start this end,
and we walk all the way
through and push anything down.
Force them into the lazy W?
Yeah, because they're all
hanging around the deep part.
Yeah.
We wanna go through
this challenge with energy.
And the only way we're
gonna be able to do that is
if we somehow score
some fish or red meat.
Although it is a great
idea, I am scared to death
that that croc is
gonna be in there
and somehow get a
hold of my or his leg.
I need to dip this pole
in there, that's right.
The croc only needs
six, eight inches of water
to get itself completely hidden.
I wonder if he's a vamoosed,
or he's just laying
low, trying to trick us.
Let's go.
Yeah.
You know, if we can get
up to that rock right there...
Yeah.
...then we've really
got them pinned in.
All right.
Yeah.
First part of the plan
is get them corralled
in a smaller space.
The second part is figure out
how to catch them and eat them.
We work too hard to
let anything get through.
Yeah.
Oh, boy.
You feeling the rain?
Yeah, it looks like it
might get really bad.
Damn it.
I've got to make
the right adjustments
on this smoker outside,
'cause right now, I'm
not comfortable leaving it
for 12 hours, although
the pieces of meat
that we have in
there are pretty big,
so they could probably do it.
I just don't wanna
risk ruining them.
So just trying to bring
the heat down a little bit,
smoke up a little bit.
But yeah, hopefully
it works well.
And we get to preserve our
meat for as long as possible.
I think this is the
wildest weather
I've ever been in my life, man.
I literally fell asleep
to warm winds,
even lay underneath the hide.
To now...
lightning, thunder,
crashing rain.
Most people would be
nervous right about now.
Not us.
We're living in a house.
We got a full on tin roof.
We got overhangs for our fire.
I hope all the other
survivalists are doing as well.
Yeah.
Yeah, praying that
it stops... this sucks.
This storm we're in
right now is probably
the hardest that
we've seen, so...
Maybe we'll be
done with it soon.
No sign of this letting up.
I'm so tired.
It was a really long night.
Usually, Africa storms
come in quick and hard,
and then they leave.
And that one was
a little different.
That one came in quick and hard,
and then just stuck
around for about six hours.
I think last night was
probably one of the worst nights
I think I've ever had
in my entire existence.
But without the
vehicles, there's no way
you would not have got
hypothermia last night.
If you were anywhere
else, like if we didn't have
the stuff, there's no
way we would have...
all made it through
to this morning.
Africa, you do not disappoint.
You put the king of
the forest in his place.
And I am humbled yet again,
and gracious that
you're blessing us
with a drier morning. Thank you.
It looks like it could start...
at any second.
We have a break
in this rain, a little bit.
I think the main thing for
today will be to make sure
that we have
firewood for tonight
and then get this roof up here.
Yeah.
Any addition to shelter
is a good addition.
-Absolutely.
-You know?
Oh, that's right overhead, too.
It's starting to rain.
Almost impossible
to do anything in.
I don't like flinging
a blade around
when you're
slipping and sliding.
You should probably
get in the truck
You put the hood on it.
I expected to come out to
no smoke at all and no coals
and have to redo it all
and I come out and
it's just churning away.
It's been raining pretty much
since we had the kudu on,
but the smoker has
been absolutely awesome.
The shelter, all accounts held
up except for one little thing,
and that's that we didn't
have the gutters on.
So we had some water come
in under the wall on my side.
Now we just gotta
finesse this wire a little bit
to get it in the right spot.
What I'm trying to do is
get it shored in real tight
so that it drips straight down,
but this left hand side needs
to be just tucked in
just a little bit more.
The change of weather
is really mixing things up,
but my eye is feeling
amazingly better.
It basically limited what I
could do, what I could see,
my comfort level, and
how I could get around.
It's so much better now
that I have two eyes back.
OK.
Looks good.
So it's raining,
and I'm pretty wet.
But honestly, this is the
best conditions to figure out
where the weak spots are
because I can actually see
where it's dripping.
All these drips are coming in.
I don't think I'm missing any.
These drips are going in there,
but this is coming
down really good.
And I think it's diverted
well in that direction.
So we're in business.
I think I'm gonna go inside.
Ugh!
Yeah.
Not. If you moved, probably.
Just barely. Not quite yet.
But you're seeing them
on me pretty good now?
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, I mean, that's fine.
Burned up a bunch of
calories with that wriggly tin
pushing down the water,
corralling those catfish.
That's calories we
pretty much don't have,
so we're really counting on...
a good reward
for all that effort.
Fish are that much
more spread out now.
I think there's
about a 0% chance
we have fish in this trap.
This pond is useless,
except for water,
-pretty much at this point.
-Yeah.
We're really out of options.
Feeling exhausted
and feeling weak.
We're literally starving.
Our literal goose
is cooked, man.
If we don't have
food in the house,
we'll be med-tapped
out of here in no time.
Yeah.
All night long and
into the morning,
it's just been a
constant drizzle.
And it just sucks.
It's just abysmal,
really soggy out there.
I'm getting cold.
And I put some
more wood on the fire.
I'm looking at the amount
of wood I'm already burning.
I started grabbing wet
wood as soon as I got out
to put it in my shelter
to start drying it.
Everything around here is wet,
and that's my biggest concern
right now is that I've
only got wet wood.
If there's another night of
rain, it's gonna be harder.
I've got to keep my
fire lit so I don't sleep
in hypothermia out here.
This is the dry wood
that I had already.
It's very limited,
but I'm drying out
some of this wet
wood that I gathered
and I'm sticking
these small sticks
underneath the
embers to dry them out
and then they won't burn.
That's my goal here is
to have a store of wood
ready to go for tonight
so that I can just stay warm.
I bent up a piece to cover
the rain, and then I bent it
at an angle so that the water
runs down off of this bend
and away from the fire pit.
So while I could tighten
up the bricks a little bit,
keep some of the wind out of it,
put forward just a little bit.
But I give away a lot of
heat coming out of this thing.
Not as much as I'd like.
I mean, I might wanna put...
another heat reflector in there.
There's a ton of shot
up coffee cans out there.
I flattened them out
and smashed them
and lined the perimeter,
inside perimeter,
of the fireplace.
It might give me
a better heat wall.
And it's not raining too hard.
All right, so we're just
gonna try and smash them up,
make them, try
to make them flat.
I'm grateful for the table
that I found at
the hunter's lodge.
I thought about
making these a chimney,
but they're so full of holes,
you know, it really wouldn't
have been conducive.
But when I flatten
them, they kind of layer
over each other and
cover up the holes.
It's probably a more
elegant way of doing that,
but that's not
how we do it here.
This place is unrelenting
and unforgiving.
And I would not have
gotten past day five
losing my partners
if I didn't have these
man-made materials
to secure a shelter for myself.
Push the bricks
a little bit closer.
Ugh...
Make a little heat wall.
My first challenge in
Zambia, we used stone.
We had nice, big, flat
pieces that could retain heat.
But metal, you get all that
same stuff with less mass.
And I kind of placed them
around the back edge,
and over the top of the
fire pit so that it would
kinda collect and
bounce more heat,
like a little heat wall.
You know, my imagination, uh,
runs wild sometimes,
but when it's harnessed
and in the right
direction, and...
it can create amazing things,
and this is a real
testament to that.
Despite all this cold air
and the wind and rain,
you can already feel the heat.
Ooh! It's still raining.
I don't know what we're
gonna do about this.
Some of those racks
with the thin slices
are probably done, but
are they too hard to get to?
Should we just bring
the whole barrel in?
Probably unrealistic.
Barrel fitting through this?
Probably not.
It's been raining pretty much
since we had the kudu on.
I've thought about
bringing it inside the shelter,
but don't know if
that's gonna work.
I wanna take this down
and deal with the meat,
but it's just we can't
really take that off
and expose all that meat
to moisture and water.
It's raining and
that's gonna ruin it.
So we've probably got 40
pounds of meat in here right now.
And just with the
way this rain's going,
we're at risk of losing
a lot, if not most of it.
We have to keep the
temperature perfect.
We have to make sure
there's enough smoke.
We have to make
sure everything's right.
Now, add to that
the rain coming in,
the cool air coming in,
it makes it extremely difficult.
Nature's given us this gift,
and now she's making us
work harder to not lose it.
I do not like this at all.
Still going.
Yeah, it's having
a real crack today.
Haven't had any sleep.
We thought, with the
vehicles, we were a little bit
more invincible than
we actually were.
Oh no, that's very bad.
It's not working.
They leak like a sieve.
The drips were on the high side.
Let me start plugging holes.
You all right?
Yeah, I'm trying
to create a... there!
Now it shouldn't
drip over there.
Oh! You're such a
clever little cookie.
So I put the stick there,
which moved the drip.
Stick on there?
That's a good move.
No.
Maybe not.
It's just decided it's
gonna find a new way.
Yeah.
This is suffering at its utmost.
We're hunkered down.
There's nowhere we can go.
If we get out in the rain,
we'll get hypothermia.
So we need to stay here.
We need to be as dry as
we can because if we aren't,
it can take us out
of this challenge.
This is how I get
through the rain.
Arms crossed, legs together,
arms over my heart.
This is tapping weather,
if you don't have
anything, right?
Can be.
It's all... all depends
on the person.
You can't even have
that thought in your head.
No.
Once you even conceive
that as a possibility,
you're already out.
I think the hardest
part of this is
we have no control over
what the weather's doing.
This could be a day thing.
It could be a week thing.
It could be the rest
of the challenge thing.
This is a mental
breaker right here.
You know, as someone who's
done so many of these challenges,
you tend to forget how this is
their first
experience in Africa.
And it's terrifying.
Storms always finish,
just a matter of when.
The sun will come out again.
You can do
anything in the world,
no matter what
situation you're in.
A struggle is what makes a hero.
Oh,
The boma's...
-definitely flooding.
-Yeah.
It's kind of getting
real close to our fire.
All right.
Holy!
The whole place
is under water now.
Yeah.
Our boma is kind of in a threat
of being flooded.
If our boma gets
flooded, our fire goes out.
Hypothermia is a real thing.
Our fire is literally life.
If we lose that,
we're out of this.
I'm happy to jump on
rotation if that helps.
No, I got it. You
guys stay warm.
It's what I'm here for.
Thank you.
Don't even worry about it.
I really... I really
don't mind one bit.
It's "Naked and Afraid," baby.
If this wasn't a part of it,
I wouldn't even be here.
"Impossible" is just a word
somebody made up one time,
because they decided
something was too hard to do,
and I don't believe
in that one bit.
I love picking up
myself by my bootstraps
and getting the job done
to not only keep me
in this competition,
but my team,
keep our fire going.
Rain always stops.
It might not be today, it
might not be tomorrow,
but eventually the storm ends.
And it's just being proactive
during the storm
while it's happening
to get through it.
You're a legend.
Thank you so much.
I'm in awe.
Steven is literally bailing us
out with a dead man's helmet.
He really has earned
his legend status.
Stop the flood. Our fire's safe.
We were about six
inches underwater.
And now, in the deepest
places, we're at like two inches.
So another beautiful
day in Africa.
Plus, from my experience,
it could always be worse.
Wee! It went.
This challenge, if it's the
sun, it's the hottest sun.
And if it's rain,
it's a monsoon.
I've gotta shore up my
shelter to keep the water out,
and I'll be a lot happier.
The wind's really
starting to pick up,
but this thing's holding strong.
I knew that was gonna happen.
The materials are brought
up like this, and there's a gap
in between where they don't
touch and overlap each other,
and so the ridge cap
will cover that gap.
I've gotta wrap
that thing on there.
It's gonna be difficult, though,
'cause it's at
its highest point,
higher than I am tall.
But right now, I'm
getting water in my shelter.
So I'm glad it happened now,
not in the middle of the night.
Ugh...
Working with this wire,
I don't have a pair of
pliers, anything to snip it,
so I just got to use friction
to bend it back and forth
until the metal
weakens and snaps.
If there was one item I
wish I had on this challenge,
it'd be a pair of pliers.
Nice.
This shelter was built
by materials that were just
by that destroyed
lodge over there
and dragged them over here
and assembled them pretty
quickly and got something.
And now... now I got the next,
you know, rest of my challenge
to really fine-tune it,
really make it, improve it.
That's really all I can do here,
is just keep making
it better and better.
So during the heat, it works,
and during the rain, it works.
And, you know, I
don't know about snow,
but it's very unlikely.
So, if that happens,
you know, well,
I think we're all in trouble.
What an absolute crappy day.
I mean, what a crappy day,
Yeah.
Not for me, buddy.
I can't believe the
consistency of the rain.
This heavy.
That long.
That's sounding creepy as hell.
We hear something awful.
Something blood curdling.
It sounds like an animal is
in pure distress, suffering,
maybe getting killed.
-Down by the water?
-Yeah.
Yeah, let's look.
Yep. You got your knife?
That crying.
How loud was that?
You see anything?
You want to cross the water now?
-Go around?
-Yeah.
All right.
I exercise a lot of caution,
and Steve's, like,
out there a little more.
But I'm hungry.
Let's get some
food in the belly.
Ugh!
-You OK?
-Ugh, yeah.
Watch your arrow. Arrow.
Oh, broadhead City.
All right.
Let's cross over and
then keep going up.
I mean, whatever it was,
it sounded like something
-was dying.
-Yeah.
Whoa, whoa, whoa. See,
see, see, see, see, see.
What in the hell?
Whatever it was,
it sounded like
something was dying.
Yeah.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
See, see, see, see,
see, see, see, see.
What in the hell?
It's a nyala, just laying there.
-All right, you got your knife?
-Yeah.
Let's walk up slow.
And let's keep our
head on a swivel.
Yeah.
-Keep our eyes open.
-Yeah.
Ugh, what the hell?
I don't know what
the hell happened to it.
You wanna flip on
over and let's just see?
OK.
I don't know, buddy, but
beggars can't be choosers.
I think, between the two of us,
we can knock it out, real quick.
Oh, those are nasty ones, too.
Sure.
Oh, yeah, we're going to be
doing tick checks tonight, baby.
Yeah.
There you go.
Let's get the guts out of it.
Yeah, right.
Thank you, brother.
Yes!
I think this is gonna
taste a lot better
than the termites I've been
eating... that is for sure.
Yeah.
You know, I was
thinking we'd do first off,
you know, we have all that wire.
-Cut off both hams.
-Yeah.
Drive a wire through.
We hang both of them
right above the fire.
That way they'll get a glaze
so the flies don't get on them.
While we process the rest of it.
So where's our big wire?
OK.
Ooh. I was a little bit nervous.
Didn't have a single hole in it,
except for my arrow.
I hate to think that it had
some kind of poisoning,
because then we're ingesting it.
On my first Africa challenge...
Oh, the pain is so bad.
I'm splitting and
tearing on the inside.
I got med-tapped
for bowel troubles.
But we need food.
It's a weird deal,
but it's fresh meat,
and I'm glad we have it.
Put this on the
top of the water lid.
-Yeah.
-And put it on the fire.
That'll be our celebration,
little steak pieces.
We're gonna eat
very well tonight.
It's gonna be a good evening.
No such thing.
Oh, this looks wonderful!
Cheers, mate!
Holy.
I did not realize how
much I needed this
until the second I
put it in my mouth.
Wow.
Oh my gosh, you
can just feel it.
Like my fingertips, man.
It's like electricity
going through your body.
I got goosebumps.
You're a hell of
a partner, buddy.
Oh.
Yeah, I do too.
You wanna go for a run?
Let’s do a 5K just, you know.
Right.
It's unbelievable how
rotten you can feel
and don't even know
it until you feel good.
Mm-hmm.
It's unbelievable how
much meat there is.
We're gonna be making
biltong, hanging everywhere.
Oh, my gosh. It's
a meat camp now.
Yeah, we got pieces cutting.
We got biltong hanging.
We have the fire
radiating off the wriggly tin
and radiating off the walls
to produce a lot
of heat and smoke
to cure the meat.
It's not a shelter.
It is a full size smoker.
In fact, I smell
like smoked meat.
Like, wait till the hyenas
and the lions smell it.
We're gonna have so
many things sniffing our door.
It's gonna be unbelievable.
Fortunately, I got Steve here.
He's mean as hell.
He can fight them off.
It's been raining for
almost 24 hours now.
A little bit short of that.
It's going to make it a lot
harder to control that smoker.
I'm just interested to check
it out and see if there's any
water coming in or if we've
got it all squared away.
-Oh!
-What?
Oh,
It has been raining nonstop
pretty much for
the last 24 hours,
maybe a little longer.
All this is wet.
I don't know whether
I'd call it survival
or just suffering.
Sitting in the car, watching
Steven single-handedly
scoop our boma out
of a flooding situation,
and sitting in there
feeling so helpless.
Ugh, OK. Fresh,
hot off the grill.
We've got some nyala steaks.
Oh, my God.
Oh, that's good now.
I'm just going to eat some more
and some more and some more.
Mm-hmm.
Oh, my gosh.
Yeah, we've got a full
evening ahead of us.
Tell you what, I'm
gonna slow down.
Hm.
Yeah.
Could there be a better day?
No.
Last night,
just wave after wave
of torrential downpour...
The rain has paused,
maybe just momentarily.
Hey, Teal, I'll need you
to help me lift this down
-if you can.
-Oh, OK.
It's not hot, and
I'll try and get
most of the weight, but... OK.
Don't forget the
top's not secure.
Yeah.
-Where are we going?
-Just down.
So this morning, I really
want to check this meat,
'cause I know that a few
things have gone awry overnight.
I was having trouble getting
coals with any of the logs
that we had just due to
how wet everything was.
Didn't get enough
of the moisture out,
which turns the inside...
You can see it's gray in
there, and pretty gross.
There are definitely
parts of this kudu leg
that we've lost.
There's definitely parts
of it that are really good,
that we're just sort
of munching on.
It's got that aged beef...
it's got that aged beef smell.
All I'm thinking it's,
"Calories in, calories in."
Unfortunately, we
lost a whole backstrap
and quite a bit of the legs.
I think the truth of the matter
is we should have
sliced it way thinner.
This is all scrap now, so
I'm going to walk this up
and dump it up at the boneyard.
OK.
Look at this green grass
that's starting to grow up.
And little sprouts everywhere.
I wonder what this
is gonna look like
in a week or two.
The environment's
changing quite significantly,
and the one thing I've
learned about survival is
we're gonna to need
to change with it.
We're going to
need to adapt with it.
Then if you don't adapt,
you're gonna be gone.
You should try to
get some rest, Lex.
It's gonna be fine.
Once the sun
breaks out a little bit,
it'll dry some of this up.
Last night was tough.
There was a river
flowing through our home.
I'd heaved gallons and
gallons of water out of our boma
to keep us alive.
My main priority out here
is to get those two people
across the finish line.
And I was going to be damned
if I was going to let us go out
on some little rainstorm.
There's nothing dry.
I mean, honestly, right
now, I just want some sleep.
Last night was an ass
kicker. It rained constantly.
There's no sleep. Soaking wet.
Still soaking wet.
You wanna have a nap, babe,
go and have a nap.
I have been awake now
for I think it's like
over 50 hours.
I'm shook.
I'd be lying if I
said I wasn't shook.
It's the first time in
this entire challenge
that I've been
really concerned
about how we're gonna survive.
Well, it definitely
feels like Armageddon,
whether it actually is or not.
I feel like right there
at the end of days.
But I mean, I'd have nothing
less for a challenge like this.
Lex...
you wanna get in here?
You should probably
get in the truck.
OK.
Here we go again.
Round three.
Mother.
Honestly, I'm not.
Come on!
Oh, my God, I'm
getting annihilated.
There's, like, leaks everywhere.
Honestly...
I wanna cry.
This is really hard.
I can suffer, and
I'll continue to suffer,
Jesus, it's hard to get by.
It's literally, just, like...
...one step at a time,
one day at a time,
one thought at a time,
because that's all I can manage.
But I'm only human.